<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A paraenesis to the Prince by VVilliam Alexander of Menstrie</title>
            <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836332</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836332</idno>
            <idno type="VID">597</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16552)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 597)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 818:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A paraenesis to the Prince by VVilliam Alexander of Menstrie</title>
                  <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Field for Edvvard Blount,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Prince = Henry, Prince of Wales.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Probably issued as part of: The monarchick tragedies: London, 1604.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:597:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:597:1"/>
            <p>A PARAENESIS to the Prince</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM ALEXANDER of Menstrie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Field (McKerrow 192)</figDesc>
               <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by RICHARD FIELD for EDVVARD BLOVNT. 1604.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:597:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:597:2"/>
            <head>A PARAENESIS to the Prince.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1</head>
               <l>LO here (braue Youth) as zeale and dutie moue,</l>
               <l>I labour (though in vaine) to find ſome gift</l>
               <l>That's worthie of thy greatneſſe, and my loue:</l>
               <l>But whil'ſt my ſelfe aboue my ſelfe I lift,</l>
               <l>And would the beſt of mine inuentions proue,</l>
               <l>I ſtand to ſtudie what ſhould be my drift:</l>
               <l>Yet this the greateſt approbation brings,</l>
               <l>Still to a Prince to ſpeake of princely things.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2</head>
               <l>When thoſe of the firſt age, that earſt did liue</l>
               <l>In ſhadowie woods, or in a humide caue;</l>
               <l>And taking that which th'earth vnforc'd did giue,</l>
               <l>VVould pay but that which Natures need did craue;</l>
               <l>Then beaſts ſuch numbers did of breath depriue:</l>
               <l>They following <hi>Amphion</hi> thoſe retires did leaue;</l>
               <l>VVho with harmonious ſounds brought them together,</l>
               <l>That each in danger might aſſiſt another.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3</head>
               <l>Then building walles, they barbarous rites diſdain'd,</l>
               <l>The ſweetneſſe of ſocietie to find,</l>
               <l>And all t'attaine that th'vnion entertain'd,</l>
               <l>As peace, religion, and a vertuous mind:</l>
               <l>That ſo they might haue reſtleſſe humors rain'd,</l>
               <l>Their liberties with lawes they ſtraight confin'd:</l>
               <l>And of the better ſort the beſt prefer'd,</l>
               <l>To chaſtiſe thoſe, againſt the lawes that err'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:597:3"/>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4</head>
               <l>I wote not if th'ambitious that aſpir'd,</l>
               <l>Ore many realmes to make themſelues a right,</l>
               <l>Or if the worlds diſorders ſo requir'd,</l>
               <l>That then had put <hi>Aſtraea</hi> to the flight;</l>
               <l>Or if t'was ſome whoſe vertues were admir'd,</l>
               <l>And eminent in all the peoples ſight,</l>
               <l>That mou'd peace-louers for to reare a throne,</l>
               <l>And giue the keyes of life and death to one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5</head>
               <l>When as that dignitie did firſt begin,</l>
               <l>T'was proper to each prouince and t'each towne;</l>
               <l>And as when <hi>Forth</hi> doth from <hi>Benlowmond</hi> rin,</l>
               <l>Shee's poore of waters, naked of renowne:</l>
               <l>But taking <hi>Teath, Allon,</hi> and <hi>Douen</hi> in,</l>
               <l>Doth grow the greater ſtill, the further downe,</l>
               <l>Till that abounding both in power and fame,</l>
               <l>She ſtriues with th'Ocean, who ſhould brooke the name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6</head>
               <l>Euen ſo thoſe ſoueraignties that once were ſmall,</l>
               <l>Still ſwallowing vp the neareſt neighbring ſtate,</l>
               <l>With a deluge of men did th'earth appall:</l>
               <l>And thus th'Egyptian <hi>Pharaohs</hi> firſt grew great;</l>
               <l>Thus did th'<hi>Aſſyrians</hi> make ſo many thrall;</l>
               <l>And thus the Romaines rear'd th'Imperiall ſeate;</l>
               <l>And thus all thoſe great States to worke haue gone,</l>
               <l>Whoſe limits and the worlds were all but one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>7</head>
               <l>But Ile not plunge in ſuch a ſtormie deepe,</l>
               <l>That neither hath a bottome, nor a ſhore;</l>
               <l>But in the duſt Ile let thoſe aſhes ſleepe,</l>
               <l>That cloath'd with purple once th'Earth did adore,</l>
               <l>Of them ſcarce now a monument we keepe,</l>
               <l>That haue ſo thundred in the world before.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:3"/>
               <l>Their ſtates that by a numbers ruine ſtood,</l>
               <l>Were founded and confounded both with blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>8</head>
               <l>If I would call antiquitie to mind,</l>
               <l>I might me for an endleſſe taske prepare.</l>
               <l>But what? ambition that was euer blind,</l>
               <l>Did get with toile that which was kept with care;</l>
               <l>And all thoſe mightie Monarchies we find</l>
               <l>Their falles were famous, as their riſings rare:</l>
               <l>And euer ſince th'vnconſtant world began,</l>
               <l>All that by vice was loſt, which vertue wan.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>9</head>
               <l>Yet regiſters of memorable things,</l>
               <l>Would helpe (great Prince) to make thy iudgement ſound,</l>
               <l>Which to the eye a perfect mirrour brings,</l>
               <l>Where all ſhould glaſſe themſelues that would be crown'd:</l>
               <l>Seeke out a ſtage where th'actors all are Kings,</l>
               <l>The parts heroicke, and the end renown'd;</l>
               <l>Which whilſt thou in thy cabinet doſt ſit,</l>
               <l>Is worthy whiles t'amuſe thy growing wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>10</head>
               <l>And do not, do not now the meanes omit</l>
               <l>To match the time that comes with it that's by,</l>
               <l>Since Hiſtorie may leade thee vnto it,</l>
               <l>A pillar whereupon good ſprites rely;</l>
               <l>The table of all times, the nurce of wit,</l>
               <l>The ſquare of reaſon, and the minds cleare eye,</l>
               <l>That leades th'vndanger'd Reader through huge harmes,</l>
               <l>Who ſtands as t'were ſecure amidſt th'alarmes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>11</head>
               <l>Nor is it good ouer braue mens liues to wander,</l>
               <l>As one that at each corner ſtands amaz'd:</l>
               <l>No, labour like ſome one thy ſelfe to render,</l>
               <l>Who to the height of glorie hath bene rais'd.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:4"/>
               <l>So <hi>Scipio Cyrus, Caeſar Alexander,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And that great Pince, chos'd him whom <hi>Homer</hi> prais'd:</l>
               <l>Or make (as which is recent and beſt knowne)</l>
               <l>Thy fathers life a patterne of thine owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <head>12</head>
               <l>Yet looking great mens liues this much impaires</l>
               <l>The profit that that benefite imparts,</l>
               <l>While as tranſported with prepoſterous cares:</l>
               <l>To imitate but ſuperficiall parts,</l>
               <l>Some for themſelues frame of their fancies ſnares,</l>
               <l>And ſhew what follie doth ore-ſway their hearts:</l>
               <l>For counterfeited things do ſtaines imbrace;</l>
               <l>And all that is affected hath no grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>13</head>
               <l>All thoſe that of thoſe outward things take hold,</l>
               <l>Do ſhow by that, they can no higher win.</l>
               <l>So to reſemble <hi>Hercules</hi> of old,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mark Antonie</hi> would beare the Lions skin;</l>
               <l>And th'heire of <hi>Alcibiades</hi> it's told,</l>
               <l>Would ſuch a courſe (though to his ſcorne) begin,</l>
               <l>Who to ſeeme like his father that was dead,</l>
               <l>Would make himſelfe to liſpe and bow his head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <head>14</head>
               <l>No, who would rightly follow ſuch as thoſe,</l>
               <l>Muſt of the better parts apply the <hi>powers;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And as th'induſtrious Bee aduis'dly goes</l>
               <l>To ſeize vpon the beſt, ſhunne baſer flowers:</l>
               <l>So where thou doſt the greateſt worth diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>To compaſſe that be prodigall of houres,</l>
               <l>And ſtudie not ſo much to ſeeme, as be:</l>
               <l>Nor ſeeme not for to know that which we ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>15</head>
               <l>And to reſemble thy renowned Syre,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt not to affect no ſlender things:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:4"/>
               <l>But matchleſſe vertues that all minds admire,</l>
               <l>Whoſe treaſure to t'his realmes great comfort brings:</l>
               <l>T'attaine to thoſe (thou Race of kings) aſpire,</l>
               <l>That they may yeeld thy fame immortall wings:</l>
               <l>And like the Eaglets prouing thus thy kind,</l>
               <l>Thou art both his of bodie and of mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <head>16</head>
               <l>Ah, be not thoſe moſt miſerable ſoules,</l>
               <l>That for to fine their iudgements neuer ſtriue,</l>
               <l>Nor will not looke vpon the learned ſcroules,</l>
               <l>That do experience to th'vnpractis'd giue;</l>
               <l>But, whilſt baſe ſlouth each better care controules,</l>
               <l>Are dead in ignorance, entomb'd aliue?</l>
               <l>Twixt ſuch and beaſts the difference is but ſmall:</l>
               <l>They vſe not reaſon, beaſts haue none at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <head>17</head>
               <l>O diuine treaſure, that the beſt ſort loues,</l>
               <l>Life of the ſoule, reformer of the will,</l>
               <l>Cleare light, that from the mind, each cloud remoues;</l>
               <l>Pure ſource of vertue, phiſicke for each ill;</l>
               <l>That in proſperitie a bridle proues,</l>
               <l>And in aduerſitie a pillar ſtill:</l>
               <l>Of thee the more men get, the more they craue;</l>
               <l>And thinke the more they get, the leſſe they haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <head>18</head>
               <l>But if that knowledge be requir'd of all,</l>
               <l>What ſhould they do this treaſure to obtaine,</l>
               <l>Whom time doth promiſe in a throne t'enſtall,</l>
               <l>Where they by it of all things muſt ordaine?</l>
               <l>If it make thoſe who by their birth were thrall,</l>
               <l>As litle kings, whil'ſt ore themſelues they raigne;</l>
               <l>Then it muſt make, when it hath throughly grac'd them,</l>
               <l>Kings more then kings, and like to him that plac'd them.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:597:5"/>
            <lg n="19">
               <head>19</head>
               <l>This is a griefe that all the world bemones,</l>
               <l>Whilſt thoſe lacke iudgement that are borne to iudge,</l>
               <l>And like to painted tombes, or guilded ſtones,</l>
               <l>Are for th'afflicted people no refuge.</l>
               <l>Kings are their kingdomes hearts, which tainted once,</l>
               <l>The bodies ſtraight muſt die, in which they lodge:</l>
               <l>And thoſe, by whoſe example many fall,</l>
               <l>Are guiltie of the murder of them all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>20</head>
               <l>The meanes that beſt make maieſtie to ſtand,</l>
               <l>Are lawes obſeru'd, good counſels brought t'effect:</l>
               <l>The Crowne the head, the Scepter deckes the hand:</l>
               <l>But onely knowledge doth the thoughts erect.</l>
               <l>Kings ſhould excell all them that they commaund,</l>
               <l>In all the parts that do procure reſpect:</l>
               <l>And this a way, to what they would, prepares,</l>
               <l>Not onely that it's good, but that it's theirs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <head>21</head>
               <l>Nor ſhould they ſeeke reſpect for, to procure</l>
               <l>With loath'd tyrannicke deedes, and guards moſt leud.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Nero</hi> did, yet could not ſo aſſure</l>
               <l>The brangling Diademe with bloud imbrude;</l>
               <l>Nor as the Perſian kings, that liu'd obſcure,</l>
               <l>And of their ſubiects rarely would be view'd.</l>
               <l>So one of them was ſecretly orethrowne,</l>
               <l>And in his place the murthrer raign'd vnknowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <head>22</head>
               <l>No, onely goodneſſe doth beget regard,</l>
               <l>And equitie doth greateſt glorie win;</l>
               <l>To plague for vice, and vertue to reward;</l>
               <l>That which they would haue done, for to begin:</l>
               <l>This is t'authoritie a powerfull guard,</l>
               <l>And makes a Princes praiſe ore all to rin;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:5"/>
               <l>VVhoſe life his ſubiects law, clear'd with his deeds,</l>
               <l>More then <hi>Iuſtinians</hi> toiles, good order breeds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <head>23</head>
               <l>All thoſe that ore th'vnbaptiz'd nations raign'd,</l>
               <l>By barbarous cuſtomes ſought t'engender feare,</l>
               <l>And with a thouſand tyrranies conſtrain'd</l>
               <l>All them that they ſubdude their yoke to beare:</l>
               <l>But thoſe whom great <hi>Iehoua</hi> hath ordain'd,</l>
               <l>Aboue the Chriſtians lawfull thrones to reare,</l>
               <l>Muſt ſeeke by worth to be obeyd by loue,</l>
               <l>So hauing raign'd below to raigne aboue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <head>24</head>
               <l>O happie <hi>Henrie,</hi> that art highly borne,</l>
               <l>Yet beautifieſt thy birth with ſignes of worth,</l>
               <l>And though a child, all childiſh toyes doeſt ſcorne,</l>
               <l>To ſhow the world thy vertues budding forth,</l>
               <l>Which may by time this glorious yle adorne,</l>
               <l>And bring eternall Trophees to the North:</l>
               <l>While as thou doeſt thy fathers forces leade,</l>
               <l>And art the hand, while as he is the head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <head>25</head>
               <l>Thou like that gallant thunderbolt of warre,</l>
               <l>Third <hi>Edwards</hi> ſonne, that was ſo much renown'd,</l>
               <l>Shalt ſhine in valour as the morning ſtarre,</l>
               <l>And pleniſh with thy praiſe the peopled round.</l>
               <l>But like to his, let nought thy fortune marre,</l>
               <l>Who in his fathers time did die vncrown'd.</l>
               <l>Long liue thy Syre, ſo all the world deſires;</l>
               <l>But longer thou; ſo natures courſe requires.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
               <head>26</head>
               <l>Although time once thee by thy birth-right owes,</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſacred honors that men moſt eſteeme,</l>
               <l>Yet flatter not thy ſelfe with thoſe faire ſhowes,</l>
               <l>Which are not altogether as they ſeeme;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:6"/>
               <l>Whoſe burd'nous waight the bearer but orethrowes,</l>
               <l>That could before of no ſuch danger deeme.</l>
               <l>Then if not arm'd in time thou make thee ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Thou doſt thy ſelfe and many a thouſand wrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="27">
               <head>27</head>
               <l>Since thou muſt manage ſuch a mightie ſtate,</l>
               <l>Now border'd but with th'Ocean and the skies;</l>
               <l>Then euen as he, who iuſtly was cal'd Great,</l>
               <l>Did (prodigall of paines to fame t'ariſe)</l>
               <l>With both the parts of worth, his worth dilate,</l>
               <l>As learn'd as valiant, and as ſtout as wiſe:</l>
               <l>So now let <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> lay the ground,</l>
               <l>Whereon thou after may thy greatneſſe found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <head>28</head>
               <l>For if addicted to a baſe repoſe,</l>
               <l>Thou didſt (as thou doſt not) miſ-ſpend thy prime;</l>
               <l>O what a faire occaſion would'ſt thou loſe,</l>
               <l>Which after would be rued, though out of time?</l>
               <l>Now to a vertuous courſe thy thoughts diſpoſe,</l>
               <l>While fancies are not glu'de with pleaſures lime.</l>
               <l>Thoſe that their youth t'a little paines engage,</l>
               <l>Acquire great eaſe vnto their perfect age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
               <head>29</head>
               <l>Now is it time with magnanimious parts,</l>
               <l>To ſhew the world what thou pretend'ſt to be,</l>
               <l>And for t'imprint in all the peoples hearts,</l>
               <l>That which thou would'ſt they ſhould expect of thee;</l>
               <l>That ſo preoccupied with ſuch deſerts,</l>
               <l>They after may applaud the heau'ns decree:</l>
               <l>When that day comes, which if it come too ſoone,</l>
               <l>Then thou and all this Iſle would be vndone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30">
               <head>30</head>
               <l>And otherwiſe what trouble ſhould'ſt thou find,</l>
               <l>If firſt not ſeiz'd of all thy ſubiects loue?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:6"/>
               <l>To deale with diuers humors, and to bind</l>
               <l>Perchance ſome mal-contents thy courſe t'approue?</l>
               <l>For then a number would ſuſpend their mind,</l>
               <l>As doubting what thou afterward might'ſt proue.</l>
               <l>And when a Realmes affections thus are cold,</l>
               <l>Of that aduantage forreiners take hold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="31">
               <head>31</head>
               <l>I graunt in this thy fortune to be good,</l>
               <l>That art t'inherit ſuch a glorious Crowne,</l>
               <l>As once deſcended from th'annointed blood,</l>
               <l>That oft hath fild the world with true renowne;</l>
               <l>The which ſtill on the top of glorie ſtood,</l>
               <l>And not ſo much as once ſeem'd to looke downe:</l>
               <l>For who thy branches to remembrance brings,</l>
               <l>Count what he liſt, he cannot but count kings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
               <head>32</head>
               <l>And pardon me, for I muſt pauſe a while,</l>
               <l>And at a thing that's worthy to b'admir'd:</l>
               <l>Since thoſe from whom thou com'ſt raign'd in this yle,</l>
               <l>Lo now of yeares euen thouſands are expir'd;</l>
               <l>Yet none could there them thrall, nor thence exile,</l>
               <l>Nor neuer fail'd the line ſo much deſir'd.</l>
               <l>The hundreth and ſeuenth parent liuing free,</l>
               <l>May leaue a neuer-conquer'd crowne to thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33">
               <head>33</head>
               <l>Nor hath this onely fortun'd but by chance,</l>
               <l>Of alterations then there had bene ſome:</l>
               <l>But that great Progenie, which ſtill did glance,</l>
               <l>Would ſo preſage the thing that was to come,</l>
               <l>That this vnited yle ſhould once aduance,</l>
               <l>And by the Lion led, all Realmes orecome:</l>
               <l>For if it kept a little free before,</l>
               <l>Now hauing much no doubt it muſt do more.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:597:7"/>
            <lg n="34">
               <head>34</head>
               <l>And though our nations long, I muſt confeſſe,</l>
               <l>Did roughly woo before that they could wed,</l>
               <l>That but endeeres the vnion we poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Neptune</hi> both combines within one bed:</l>
               <l>All th'ancient iniuries this doth redreſſe,</l>
               <l>And buries that which many a battell bred.</l>
               <l>A diſcord reconcil'd (if wrath expire)</l>
               <l>Doth breed the greateſt loue and moſt entire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
               <head>35</head>
               <l>Of Englands <hi>Marie</hi> had it bene the chance</l>
               <l>T'haue made King <hi>Philip</hi> father of a ſonne,</l>
               <l>The haughtie-minded Spaniards pride t'aduance,</l>
               <l>All Albions beautie had bene quite orerunne;</l>
               <l>Or yet if Scotlands <hi>Marie</hi> had heir'd France,</l>
               <l>This yle to liue in thraldome had begunne:</l>
               <l>Of which, if that a ſtranger brookt a part,</l>
               <l>That would to take the other meanes impart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="36">
               <head>36</head>
               <l>Thus were we from two dangers twiſe preſeru'd,</l>
               <l>When as we ſeem'd without recouerie loſt,</l>
               <l>As thoſe that from their freedome freely ſweru'd,</l>
               <l>And ſuffred ſtrangers of our bounds to boſt:</l>
               <l>Yet were we for this happie time preſeru'd,</l>
               <l>And but to hold it deare a little croſt,</l>
               <l>That of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> might th'vndanted race,</l>
               <l>Dominions equall with their minds imbrace,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="37">
               <head>37</head>
               <l>Of that bleſt progenie th'experienc'd worth,</l>
               <l>Hath of the people a conceit procur'd,</l>
               <l>That from the race it neuer can go forth,</l>
               <l>But as hereditary is thought affur'd:</l>
               <l>Thus (ſonne of that great monarke of the North)</l>
               <l>They are t'obedience happily inur'd,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:7"/>
               <l>Ore whom thou art expected for to raigne,</l>
               <l>To haue good anceſtors t'is a great gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38">
               <head>38</head>
               <l>He that by tyrannie his throne doth reare,</l>
               <l>And diſpoſſeſſe another of his right,</l>
               <l>Whoſe panting heart dare neuer truſt his eare;</l>
               <l>For being odious in the peoples ſight,</l>
               <l>Whilſt he both hath and giues great cauſe of feare,</l>
               <l>Is ſpoyling all, at laſt ſpoil'd of the light:</l>
               <l>And thoſe that are deſcended of his blood,</l>
               <l>Ere that they be beleeu'd, muſt long be good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="39">
               <head>39</head>
               <l>Yet though we ſee it is an eaſie thing,</l>
               <l>For ſuch a one his ſtate for to maintaine,</l>
               <l>Who being by his birth-right borne a King,</l>
               <l>Doth with the countries loue the crowne obtaine,</l>
               <l>The ſame doth many to confuſion bring,</l>
               <l>Whilſt for that cauſe they care not how they raigne.</l>
               <l>O, neuer throne eſtabiſh'd was ſo ſure,</l>
               <l>Whoſe fall a vitious Prince might not procure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40">
               <head>40</head>
               <l>Thus do a number to deſtruction runne:</l>
               <l>And ſo did <hi>Tarquin</hi> once abuſe his place,</l>
               <l>Who for th'infamous life he had begunne,</l>
               <l>Was barr'd from <hi>Rome,</hi> and ruin'd all his race.</l>
               <l>So he whoſe father of no King was ſonne,</l>
               <l>Was father to no King, but in diſgrace</l>
               <l>From <hi>Sicile</hi> baniſh'd with the peoples hate,</l>
               <l>Did die in <hi>Corinth</hi> in a baſe eſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="41">
               <head>41</head>
               <l>And as that Monarke merites endleſſe praiſe,</l>
               <l>Who hath firſt founded ſome renown'd Empire;</l>
               <l>So all the world with ſcornefull eyes may gaze</l>
               <l>On their degener'd ſtemmes that might aſpire,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:8"/>
               <l>As hauing greater power their power to raiſe,</l>
               <l>Yet of their race the ruine do conſpire,</l>
               <l>And for their wrong-ſpent life with ſhame do end:</l>
               <l>Kings chaſtis'd once, they get no time t'amend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42">
               <head>42</head>
               <l>Thoſe that repoſing on their princely name,</l>
               <l>Can neuer giue themſelues to care for ought,</l>
               <l>But for their pleaſures euery thing would frame,</l>
               <l>As all were made for them, and they for nought,</l>
               <l>Once th'earth will ſpoile their bodies, men their fame,</l>
               <l>Though whilſt they liue, all for their eaſe be wrought;</l>
               <l>And thoſe conceits on which they do depend,</l>
               <l>Do but betray their fortunes in the end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="43">
               <head>43</head>
               <l>This ſelfe conceit, doth ſo the iudgement ſmoke,</l>
               <l>That when ought well ſucceeds with ſome through it,</l>
               <l>They on the ſame with great affection looke,</l>
               <l>And ſcorne th'aduiſe of others to admit.</l>
               <l>Thus did braue <hi>Charles</hi> the laſt Burgundian Duke,</l>
               <l>Deare buy a battell purchas'd by his wit,</l>
               <l>Who euer after truſting to the ſame,</l>
               <l>Was brought vnto confuſion and to ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44">
               <head>44</head>
               <l>O ſacred counſell, quinteſſence of ſoules;</l>
               <l>Strength of the common-wealth, that chaines the fates,</l>
               <l>And euery danger, ere it come, controules;</l>
               <l>The anker of all realmes, ſtaffe of all ſtates,</l>
               <l>O ſure foundation that no tempeſt foules,</l>
               <l>On which are builded glorious workes, great ſeates:</l>
               <l>If ought with thoſe ſucceed that ſcorne thy care,</l>
               <l>It's but by chance, and drawes them in a ſnare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="45">
               <head>45</head>
               <l>Thriſe happie is the King, that hath the grace</l>
               <l>To chuſe a counſell whereon to rely,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:8"/>
               <l>That loues his perſon, and reſpects his place,</l>
               <l>And like <hi>Ariſtides</hi> can whiles caſt by</l>
               <l>All priuate grudge, the publicke cares t'embrace,</l>
               <l>Voide of ambition, hatred or enuie;</l>
               <l>And that they be not to betray their ſeates,</l>
               <l>The partiall Penſioners of forreine ſtates.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="46">
               <head>46</head>
               <l>None ſhould but thoſe of that graue number boſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe liues haue long with many vertues glaunc'd,</l>
               <l>As Rome reſpected the Patritians moſt,</l>
               <l>The Nobles (if themſelues) ſhould firſt b'aduanc'd;</l>
               <l>Yet in ſuch ſort that others haue not loſt,</l>
               <l>All hope to riſe, then worth would not b'enhaunc'd:</l>
               <l>For painefull vertue in her courſe would tire,</l>
               <l>Were not ſhe hopes t'haue honor for her hire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="47">
               <head>47</head>
               <l>But ſuch as thoſe a Prince ſhould moſt eſchue,</l>
               <l>That dignities do curiouſly affect;</l>
               <l>Who doth for any publike charge purſue,</l>
               <l>He muſt haue ſome particular reſpect.</l>
               <l>They ſhould be godly, prudent, ſecret, true,</l>
               <l>Of whom a King his Councell ſhould erect;</l>
               <l>And he, whilſt they aduiſe of zeale and loue,</l>
               <l>Should not the manieſt, but the beſt approue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="48">
               <head>48</head>
               <l>There needs a great diſcretion for to know,</l>
               <l>To ballance each opinion in his mind:</l>
               <l>But ah this doth the iudgement oft orethrow,</l>
               <l>While as he comes within himſelfe confin'd,</l>
               <l>And of the Senate would but make a ſhow,</l>
               <l>For to confirme that which he hath deſign'd;</l>
               <l>As one that onely hath whereon to reſt,</l>
               <l>For counſellers his thoughts, their ſeate his breſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:597:9"/>
            <lg n="49">
               <head>49</head>
               <l>But what auailes a Senate in this ſort,</l>
               <l>Whoſe pow'r within the Capitoll is pent?</l>
               <l>A blaſt of breath that doth for nought import,</l>
               <l>But mocks the world with th'vnperform'd intent:</l>
               <l>Thoſe are the councels that great ſtates ſupport,</l>
               <l>Which neuer are made knowne but by th'euent,</l>
               <l>Not thoſe where wiſe men matters do propoſe,</l>
               <l>And fooles thereafter as they pleaſe diſpoſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="50">
               <head>50</head>
               <l>Nor is this all that ought to be requir'd</l>
               <l>In this aſſembly, that's the kingdomes ſoule,</l>
               <l>That with a knowledge more then rare inſpir'd,</l>
               <l>A common wealth like <hi>Platoes</hi> in a ſcroule</l>
               <l>They can paint forth; meanes muſt by them b'acquird,</l>
               <l>The torrent of diſorder to controule,</l>
               <l>And arming with authoritie their lines,</l>
               <l>To act with iuſtice that which wit deſignes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="51">
               <head>51</head>
               <l>Great Empreſſe of this vniuerſall frame,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Atlas</hi> on whoſe ſhoulders States are ſtaid,</l>
               <l>That ſwayſt the raines that all the world do tame,</l>
               <l>And makes men good by force with red arraid,</l>
               <l>Diſorders enemie, virgin without blame,</l>
               <l>Within whoſe ballance good and bad are weigh'd;</l>
               <l>O ſoueraigne of all vertues, without thee</l>
               <l>Nor peace, nor warre can entertained be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="52">
               <head>52</head>
               <l>Thou from confuſion all things haſt redeem'd:</l>
               <l>Th'aſſembly of th'Amphictions had bene vaine,</l>
               <l>And all thoſe Senates that were moſt eſteem'd,</l>
               <l>Wer't not by thee their councels crown'd remaine;</l>
               <l>And all thoſe lawes had but dead letters ſeem'd,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Solon</hi> or <hi>Lycurgus</hi> did ordaine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:9"/>
               <l>Wer't not thy ſword made all alike to die;</l>
               <l>And not the weake, while as the ſtrong ſcap'd by.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="53">
               <head>53</head>
               <l>O not without great cauſe all th'Ancients did</l>
               <l>Paint Magiſtrates, that were t'explane the lawes,</l>
               <l>Not hauing hands, ſo briberie to forbid,</l>
               <l>Which them from doing right too oft withdrawes:</l>
               <l>And with a veile the Iudges eyes were hid,</l>
               <l>Who ſhould not ſee the partie, but the cauſe.</l>
               <l>Gods Deputies that his tribunall reare,</l>
               <l>Should haue a patent, not a partiall eare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="54">
               <head>54</head>
               <l>The lacke of Iuſtice hath huge euils begun,</l>
               <l>That by no meanes could be repair'd againe.</l>
               <l>The famous Sire of that more famous ſonne,</l>
               <l>For whom, while as he ſleeping did remaine,</l>
               <l>One did appeale, till that his ſleepe was done:</l>
               <l>And whom a widdow did diſcharge to raigne,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he had not time on plaints t'attend,</l>
               <l>Did loſe his life for ſuch a fault in th'end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="55">
               <head>55</head>
               <l>This Iuſtice is the vertue moſt diuine,</l>
               <l>Which ſhowes kings like the King of kings inclin'd,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſure foundations nought can vndermine,</l>
               <l>If once within a conſtant breſt confin'd:</l>
               <l>For otherwiſe ſhe cannot clearely ſhine,</l>
               <l>While as the Magiſtrate oft changing mind,</l>
               <l>Doth whiles aduance, and whiles is ſlow to ſtrike,</l>
               <l>And being ſuggeſted, is not ſtill alike.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="56">
               <head>56</head>
               <l>Vſe mercie freely, Iuſtice as conſtrain'd:</l>
               <l>Th'one muſt be done, though th'other be more deare:</l>
               <l>And whiles the forme may make the deed diſdain'd,</l>
               <l>Whilſt Iuſtice taſts of Tyrrannie too neare:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:10"/>
               <l>One may be iuſtly, yet in rage arraign'd,</l>
               <l>Whilſt reaſon rul'd by paſſions doth appeare.</l>
               <l>Once <hi>Socrates,</hi> becauſe ore-com'd with ire,</l>
               <l>Did from correcting one (till calm'd) retire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="57">
               <head>57</head>
               <l>Thoſe that want meanes their anger to aſſwage,</l>
               <l>Do others oft, whiles rob themſelues of breath.</l>
               <l>Fierce <hi>Valentinian</hi> ſurfetting in rage,</l>
               <l>By burſting of a veine did bleed to death:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Theodoſius</hi> ſtill, but then thought ſage,</l>
               <l>Caus'd murther thouſands being drunke with wrath,</l>
               <l>Who to preuent the like opprobrious crime,</l>
               <l>Caus'd ſtill ſuſpend his edicts for a time.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="58">
               <head>58</head>
               <l>All th'actions of a vertuous king proceed</l>
               <l>Forth from the ſource of a paternall loue,</l>
               <l>To chaſtiſe or cheriſh as Realmes haue need,</l>
               <l>For which he more then for himſelfe doth moue;</l>
               <l>Who many a millions eaſe that way to breed,</l>
               <l>Makes ſometime ſome his indignation proue;</l>
               <l>And like to <hi>Codrus,</hi> cares not death t'embrace,</l>
               <l>If for the countries good, and peoples peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="59">
               <head>59</head>
               <l>This Ladie, that ſo long vnarm'd hath ſtray'd,</l>
               <l>Now holds the ballance, and doth draw the ſword,</l>
               <l>And neuer was more gloriouſly array'd,</l>
               <l>Nor in ſhort time did greater good affoord.</l>
               <l>The ſtate that to confuſion ſeem'd betraid,</l>
               <l>And could of nought but bloud and wrongs record,</l>
               <l>Now freed from trouble and inteſtine rage,</l>
               <l>Doth boaſt for to reſtore the golden age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="60">
               <head>60</head>
               <l>Thus doth thy father (generous Prince) prepare</l>
               <l>A way for thee t'attaine t'immortall fame,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:10"/>
               <l>And layes the grounds of greatneſſe with ſuch care,</l>
               <l>That thou maiſt build great workes vpon the ſame.</l>
               <l>Then ſince thou art to haue a field ſo faire,</l>
               <l>Whereas thou once maiſt eternize thy name,</l>
               <l>Begin, while as a greater light thine ſmothers,</l>
               <l>And learne to rule thy ſelfe, ere thou rul'ſt others.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="61">
               <head>61</head>
               <l>For ſtill true magnanimitie we find,</l>
               <l>Doth harbor ſoone in an Heroicke breſt.</l>
               <l>To match <hi>Miltiades,</hi> whoſe glorie ſhin'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> (a child) was rob'd of reſt.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtriue to be a Monarke of thy mind:</l>
               <l>For as t'attempt great things, all elſe deteſt,</l>
               <l>A generous emulation ſpurres the ſprite;</l>
               <l>So vaine ambition blinds the courage quite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="62">
               <head>62</head>
               <l>Whilſt of th'illuſtrious liues thou look'ſt the ſtorie,</l>
               <l>Abhorre thoſe Tyrants that ſtill ſwim'd in bloud;</l>
               <l>And follow thoſe, that to their endleſſe glorie,</l>
               <l>High in their ſubiects loue by vertue ſtood.</l>
               <l>O! be like him, who on a time was ſorie,</l>
               <l>Becauſe, while as he chanc'd to do no good,</l>
               <l>There hapned but one day for to expire:</l>
               <l>That was the worlds delight, the heau'ns deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="63">
               <head>63</head>
               <l>But as ſome gaine great ſtates by being humaine,</l>
               <l>Some through their lenitie loſe what they haue.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Englands</hi> ſixt <hi>Henry</hi> could not liue and raigne,</l>
               <l>But being ſimple, did huge foiles receaue:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Scipioes</hi> armie mutined in <hi>Spaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That through his gentleneſſe their charge did leaue.</l>
               <l>O! to the ſtate it brings great profit oft,</l>
               <l>For to be whiles ſeuere, and not ſtill ſoft.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:597:11"/>
            <lg n="64">
               <head>64</head>
               <l>To guide his Courſers warely through the skie,</l>
               <l>Earſt <hi>Phoebus</hi> did his <hi>Phaëton</hi> require,</l>
               <l>Saying, from the ſtraight way if he ſwaru'd by,</l>
               <l>The heau'ns would burne, or th'earth would be on fire.</l>
               <l>So doth twixt two Extremes each vertue lie,</l>
               <l>To which the pureſt ſprites ought to aſpire:</l>
               <l>He liues moſt ſure that no extreame doth touch,</l>
               <l>Nothing would be too litle, nor too much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="65">
               <head>65</head>
               <l>Some kings, whom all men did in hatred hold,</l>
               <l>Whoſe breaſts with auaritious thoughts were torne,</l>
               <l>As wretch'd <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> ſought to gather gold</l>
               <l>By baſe and abiect meanes, that braue minds ſcorne.</l>
               <l>Such whilſt they ſeeke not t'haue their greed control'd,</l>
               <l>But how they may their treaſuries adorne,</l>
               <l>Are, though like <hi>Croeſus</hi> rich, whil'ſt wealth them blinds,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill as poore as <hi>Irus</hi> in their minds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="66">
               <head>66</head>
               <l>And ſome againe as fooliſh fancies moue,</l>
               <l>That praiſe without diſcretion do purſue,</l>
               <l>In ſtead of liberall, prodigall do proue;</l>
               <l>Then whilſt their treaſures they exhauſted view,</l>
               <l>With Subſidies their ſubiects do commoue,</l>
               <l>And ſpoile whole realmes for to enrich a few,</l>
               <l>Whilſt with authoritie their pride they cloake,</l>
               <l>That ought to die by ſmoake for ſelling ſmoake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="67">
               <head>67</head>
               <l>But ô the Prince moſt loath'd in euery land,</l>
               <l>It's one that's giuen to luſt, who hardly can</l>
               <l>Free from ſome great miſchiefe a long time ſtand;</l>
               <l>For all the world his deeds with hatred ſcan.</l>
               <l>Should he that hath the honour to command</l>
               <l>The nobleſt creature (great Gods image) man,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:11"/>
               <l>Be to the vileſt vice, the bafeſt ſlaue,</l>
               <l>The bodies plague, ſoules death, and honors graue?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="68">
               <head>68</head>
               <l>Th'vnnaturall monſter, that retir'd apart,</l>
               <l>Amongſt his concubines began to ſpinne,</l>
               <l>Tooke with the habite too a womans heart,</l>
               <l>And ended that which <hi>Ninus</hi> did begin.</l>
               <l>Faint-hearted <hi>Xerxes,</hi> that did gifts impart</l>
               <l>To them that could deuiſe new waies to ſinne,</l>
               <l>Though back't with worlds of men in th'enemies ſight,</l>
               <l>Had not the courage for to ſee them fight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="69">
               <head>69</head>
               <l>Thus doth ſoft pleaſure but abaſe the mind,</l>
               <l>And making one to ſeruile thoughts deſcend,</l>
               <l>Doth make the bodie weake, the iudgement blind,</l>
               <l>A hatefull life, an ignominious end:</l>
               <l>Where thoſe that did this raging tyrant bind</l>
               <l>With vertues chaines, their triumphes to attend,</l>
               <l>Haue by that meanes a greater glorie gain'd,</l>
               <l>Then all the victories that they attain'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="70">
               <head>70</head>
               <l>The valorous <hi>Perſian</hi> that refus'd t'haue gaz'd</l>
               <l>Vpon <hi>Pantheas</hi> beauties, t'eaſe his toiles,</l>
               <l>His glorie by that continencie rais'd,</l>
               <l>More then by <hi>Babylons</hi> and <hi>Lidiaes</hi> ſpoiles:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Macedonian</hi> Monarke was more prais'd,</l>
               <l>Then for triumphing ore ſo many ſoiles,</l>
               <l>That of his greateſt foe (though beauteous ſeene)</l>
               <l>He chaſtly entertain'd the captiu'd Queene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="71">
               <head>71</head>
               <l>Thus haue ſtil-gas'd-at Monarkes much a do,</l>
               <l>That all the worlds diſorders to redreſſe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:12"/>
               <l>Should ſhine like to the Sunne, the which ſtill lo</l>
               <l>The more it mounts aloft, doth ſeeme the leſſe:</l>
               <l>They ſhould with confidence go freely to,</l>
               <l>And truſting to their worth, their will expreſſe:</l>
               <l>Not like French <hi>Lewis</hi> th'eleuenth, that did maintaine,</l>
               <l>That who could not diſſemble, could not raigne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="72">
               <head>72</head>
               <l>But for to guard their ſtate, the ſtrongeſt barre,</l>
               <l>And beſt refuge in euery dangerous ſtorme,</l>
               <l>It is, to be a gallant man of warre,</l>
               <l>And t'haue a heart t'attempt, hands to performe;</l>
               <l>Not that they hazard ſhould their ſtate too farre,</l>
               <l>And to each ſouldiers courſe their courſe conforme.</l>
               <l>The skilfull Pilots at the rudder ſit:</l>
               <l>Let others vſe their ſtrength, and them their wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="73">
               <head>73</head>
               <l>In <hi>Mars</hi>-his myſteries t'acquire renowne,</l>
               <l>It giues Kings glorie, and aſſures their place:</l>
               <l>It breeds them a reſpect amongſt their owne,</l>
               <l>And makes their neighbours feare to loſe their grace.</l>
               <l>Still all thoſe ſhould, that loue to keepe their crowne,</l>
               <l>In peace prepare for warre, in warre for peace:</l>
               <l>For as all feare a Prince that dare attempt,</l>
               <l>The want of courage brings one in contempt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="74">
               <head>74</head>
               <l>And (royall Of-ſpring) that haſt cauſe t'aſpire,</l>
               <l>As one to whom thy birth high hopes aſſign'd,</l>
               <l>This well becomes the courage of thy Sire,</l>
               <l>That traines thee vp according to thy kind.</l>
               <l>He, though the world his proſp'rous raigne admire,</l>
               <l>In which his ſubiects ſuch a comfort find,</l>
               <l>Hath (if once mou'd the bloudie art t'imbrace)</l>
               <l>That wit for to make warre, which now keepes peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:597:12"/>
            <lg n="75">
               <head>75</head>
               <l>And ô how this (deare Prince) the people charmes,</l>
               <l>That flocke about thee whiles in rauiſh'd bands,</l>
               <l>To ſee thee young, yet manage ſo thine armes,</l>
               <l>And haue <hi>Mineruaes</hi> mind, <hi>Bellonaes</hi> hands.</l>
               <l>This exerciſe thy tender courage warmes;</l>
               <l>And ſtill true greatneſſe but by vertue ſtands:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> ſaid, no King could be</l>
               <l>More great, vnleſſe more vertuous, then he.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="76">
               <head>76</head>
               <l>Although that all of thee great things expect,</l>
               <l>Thou as too litle mak'ſt their hopes aſham'd:</l>
               <l>As he that on <hi>Olympus</hi> did detect</l>
               <l>The famous <hi>Thebans</hi> foote, his bodie fram'd:</l>
               <l>By thy beginnings ſo we may collect,</l>
               <l>How great thy worth by time may be proclaim'd:</l>
               <l>For who thy actions doth remarke, may ſee,</l>
               <l>That there be many <hi>Caeſars</hi> within thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="77">
               <head>77</head>
               <l>Though many a realme by long experience finds,</l>
               <l>That all the greateſt bleſſings peace imparts,</l>
               <l>As that which to good order all men binds;</l>
               <l>Yet breeds this Iſle, ſtill populous in all parts,</l>
               <l>Such vigorous bodies, and ſuch reſtleſſe minds,</l>
               <l>That they diſdaine t'imbrace Mechanicke arts;</l>
               <l>And being haughtie cannot liue in reſt:</l>
               <l>Yea, t'hold ſuch idle, it's a dangerous peſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="78">
               <head>78</head>
               <l>Earſt prudent <hi>Cato</hi> told in ſome few howres,</l>
               <l>What danger to the <hi>Romaines</hi> did redound,</l>
               <l>While as they raz'd the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> towres;</l>
               <l>By which, while as they ſtood, ſtill meanes were found</l>
               <l>With others harmes to exerciſe their powers;</l>
               <l>The want whereof their greatneſſe did confound.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:13"/>
               <l>For when no more with forraine foes imbroil'd,</l>
               <l>Straight with inteſtine warres the ſtate was ſpoil'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="79">
               <head>79</head>
               <l>No, ſince this ſoyle that in great ſprites abounds,</l>
               <l>Can hardly nurce her nurcelings all in peace,</l>
               <l>Then let vs keepe her boſome free from wounds,</l>
               <l>And ſpend our furie in ſome forraine place.</l>
               <l>There is no wall can limite now our bounds,</l>
               <l>But all the world will need walles in ſhort ſpace,</l>
               <l>T'hold backe our troupes from ſeizing on new thrones:</l>
               <l>The marble chaire muſt paſſe the Ocean once.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="80">
               <head>80</head>
               <l>What furour ore my iudgement doth preuaile?</l>
               <l>Me thinkes I ſee all th'earth glaunce with our armes,</l>
               <l>And groning <hi>Neptune</hi> charg'd with many a ſaile:</l>
               <l>I heare the thundring trumpet found th'alarmes,</l>
               <l>Whilſt all the neighbring nations do looke pale;</l>
               <l>Such ſudden feare each panting heart diſarmes,</l>
               <l>To ſee thoſe martiall minds together gone,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Lion</hi> and the <hi>Leopard</hi> in one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="81">
               <head>81</head>
               <l>I <hi>(Henrie)</hi> hope with this mine eyes to feed,</l>
               <l>Whilſt, ere thou wearſt a crowne, thou wear'ſt a ſhield,</l>
               <l>And when thou making thouſands for to bleed,</l>
               <l>That dare behold thy count'nance and not yeeld,</l>
               <l>Sturres through the bloudie duſt a foaming ſteed,</l>
               <l>An intereſted witneſſe in the field,</l>
               <l>I may amongſt thoſe bands thy Grace attend,</l>
               <l>And be thy <hi>Homer,</hi> when the warres do end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="82">
               <head>82</head>
               <l>But ſtay, where flieſt thou (Muſe) ſo farre aſtray?</l>
               <l>And whilſt affection doth thy courſe command,</l>
               <l>Dares thus aboue thy reach attempt a way,</l>
               <l>To ſing to th'Heire of <hi>Albions</hi> warlike land,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:597:13"/>
               <l>Who gotten hath, his generous thoughts t'array</l>
               <l>A Royall gift out of a Royall hand;</l>
               <l>And hath before his eyes, that type of worth,</l>
               <l>That ſtarre of ſtate, that Pole that guides the North.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="83">
               <head>83</head>
               <l>Yet ore thy father lo (ſuch is thy fate)</l>
               <l>Thou haſt this vantage, that may profit thee,</l>
               <l>An orphan'd Infant ſetled in his ſeate,</l>
               <l>He greater then himſelfe could neuer ſee:</l>
               <l>Where thou maiſt learne by him the art of State,</l>
               <l>And by another what thy ſelfe ſhouldſt be:</l>
               <l>Whilſt that which he had onely but heard told,</l>
               <l>Thou may'ſt practis'd in all his courſe behold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="84">
               <head>84</head>
               <l>And this aduantage long mought thou retaine,</l>
               <l>By which to make thee bleſt the heau'ns conſpire;</l>
               <l>And labour of his worth to make thy gaine,</l>
               <l>To whoſe perfections thou maiſt once aſpire;</l>
               <l>When as thou ſhew'ſt thy ſelfe, whil'ſt thou doſt raigne,</l>
               <l>A Sonne that's worthie of ſo great a Sire,</l>
               <l>And with his Scepters, and the peoples harts,</l>
               <l>Doſt ſtill inherite his Heroicke parts.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. A.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
